<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short and plaine dialogue concerning the vnlawfulnes of playing at cards or tables, or any other game consisting in chance Offered to the religious consideration of all such as make conscience of all their waies.</title>
            <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836595</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03232)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 485:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short and plaine dialogue concerning the vnlawfulnes of playing at cards or tables, or any other game consisting in chance Offered to the religious consideration of all such as make conscience of all their waies.</title>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Richard Boile,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author identified in the dedicatory epistle, which is dated: the first of Ianuarie 1593.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gambling --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:879:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SHORT AND PLAINE DIALOGVE CONCERNING THE vnlawfulnes of playing at Cards <hi>or Tables, or any other game conſiſting in chance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OFFERED TO THE RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious conſideration of all ſuch as make conſcience of all their waies.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. THESSAL. 5.21.</bibl>
               <p>Trie all things and keepe that which is good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Richard Boile.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:879:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:879:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER LIONEL MADDISON, Maior, the Aldermen his Brethren, and</hi> the godly Burgeſſes of Newcaſtle vpon Tine; <hi>IAMES BALMFORD</hi> Wiſheth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his righteouſneſſe, that other things may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which heretofore I haue propounded to you (right Worſhipfull and beloued) in teaching, I doe now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to all men by printing, to wit, mine opinion of the vnlawfulnes of games con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in chance. My deſirets either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, if I erre in iudgement, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of ſo leud a practiſe. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I erre or no (which yet I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtand,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3.7.</note> for I ought not to teach
<pb facs="tcp:879:3"/>an vntruth, though to Gods glorie) yet there is none, zealous indeede againſt ſin, deſirous from the heart to reclaime ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and who deeply conſidereth the grieuous abuſes, which accompanie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and carding (as horrible ſwearing, dangerous quarelling, loſſe (I ſay not of good houres, but) of nights and daies, and the pitifull vndoing of too too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) but will remember that<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.12.</note> all things are not expedient, which are lawfull, and therefore abſtaine from ſuch Heatheniſh paſtimes, that, if by their example they cannot reforme, they may be ſure<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.9.</note> they doe not confirme gameſters in their inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate walking. Which reſpect, the <hi>7.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction forbidding Miniſters to vſe theſe vnlawfull games, may be ſuppoſed to haue. Now that which authoritie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth of Miniſters, doth Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of all true Profeſſors. For as the one are to be<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tit 5 3.</note> enſamples to the flocke, ſo the other are to be<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.15</note> lights in the world. And therefore as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.10.13.</note> If meate
<pb facs="tcp:879:3"/>offend my brother, I will eate no fleſh while the world ſtandeth: ſo euery true Chriſtian ſhould ſay, and that with more reſolution (for Play is not ſo neceſſarie as meate) If play offend my brother, who ſeeing me, hauing knowledge, play, is boldned to follow gaming, I will not play while the world ſtandeth. Which care vnto edification, if all, who haue the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.16.17.</note> word in their mouthes, and would not bee thought to hate to bee reformed, would manifeſt in their ſincere conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and if Magiſtrates, who ſhould not<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> carrie the ſword in vaine, would doe what they may by<note n="*" place="margin">33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 9 5. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> law, to baniſh theſe forbidden paſt times, or rather loſt-times, I doubt not, but that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing againſt them would more mightily preuaile, and this good would come of it, many would applie themſelues to better exerciſes, there would bee leſſe time miſpent in Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and God leſſe prouoked to diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt vs. But theſe things I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb facs="tcp:879:4"/>to the conſideration of the wiſe, and this my Dialogue to the iudgement of the godlie, chiefly to you, whoſe good I wiſh eſpecially.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell:</salute>
               <dateline>From my ſtudie <date>the firſt of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie 1593.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:879:4"/>
            <head>A SHORT AND PLAINE DIALOGVE CONCERNING THE vnlawfulnes of playing at Cards or Tables, or any other game conſiſting of chance.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſſor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, howſoeuer I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that which I reade in the common places of <hi>Peter Martyr, par.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 525 <hi>b,</hi> that Dice (condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both by the Ciuill lawes, and by the Fathers) are therefore vnlawfull, becauſe they depend vpon chance: yet not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with that which he writeth of Table-playing, <hi>pag.</hi> 526. <hi>b,</hi> I would craue your opinion concerning playing at Tables and Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preacher.</speaker>
               <p>Sauing the iudgement of ſo excellent a Diuine, ſo farre as I can learne out of Gods word, Cardes and
<pb facs="tcp:879:5"/>Tables ſeeme to mee no more lawfull (though leſſe offenſiue) than Dice. For Table-playing is no whit the more lawfull, becauſe <hi>Plato</hi> compares the life of man thereunto, than a theefe is the more iuſtifiable, becauſe Chriſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, to Burglarie in the night, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.43.44. Againe, if Dice be wholly euill, becauſe they wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon chance, then Tables and Cards muſt needes be ſomewhat euill, becauſe they ſomewhat depend vpon chance. Therefore conſider well this reaſon, which condemneth the one as well as the other: Lots are not to bee vſed in ſport; but games conſiſting in chance, as Dice, Cardes, Tables, are lots: therefore not to be vſed in ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prof.</speaker>
               <p>For my better inſtruction, proue that Lots are not to be vſed in ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Conſider with regard theſe three things:<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.48. 1. Cor. 11.16.</note> Firſt, that wee reade not in the Scriptures that Lots were vſed but only in ſerious matters both by the Iewes, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 18.10. and Gentiles, <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.7. Secondly, that a Lot in the nature ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of doth as neceſſarily ſuppoſe the ſpecial
<pb facs="tcp:879:5"/>prouidence and determining preſence of God, as an oth in the nature therof doth ſuppoſe the teſtifying preſence of God. Yea ſo, that (as in an oth, ſo) in a lot pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is expreſſed or to bee vnderſtoode, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.41. Thirdly, that the proper end of a Lot (as of an oth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.) is to end a controuerſie: and therefore for your better inſtruction examine theſe reaſons. Whatſoeuer directly, or of it ſefe, or in a ſpeciall manner, tendeth to the aduancing of the name of God, is to be vſed religiouſly, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6.7. and not to be vſed in ſport: as wee are not to pray or ſweare in ſport, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.2. but the vſe of Lots, directly of it ſelfe, and in a ſpeciall manner tendeth to the aduancing of the name of God, in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to his ſpeciall prouidence in the whole and immediate diſpoſing of the Lot, and expecting the euent, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.24.26. Therefore the vſe of Lots is not to be in ſport. Againe, we are not to tempt the Almightie by a vaine deſire of manifeſtation of his power and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall prouidence, <hi>Pſal. 78.18.19. Eſa. 7.12. Matth. 4.6.7.</hi> But by vſing Lots in ſport
<pb facs="tcp:879:6"/>we tempt the Almightie, vainly deſiring the manifeſtation of his ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his immediate diſpoſing, Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c. Laſtly, whatſoeuer God hath ſanctified to a proper end, is not to bee peruerted to a worſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.12.13. But God hath ſanctified Lots to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end, namely to end controuerſies, <hi>Num.</hi> 26.55. Pro. 18.18. therefore man is not to peruert them to a worſe: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to play, and by playing to get away another mans money, which without controuerſie is his owne. For the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying is, <hi>Sine lucro friget luſus,</hi> No gaining, cold gaming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>God hath ſanctified Pſalmes to the praiſe of his name, and bread and wine to repreſent the bodie and bloud of our crucified Sauiour, which be holie ends: and the children of God may ſing Pſalmes to make themſelues merie in the Lord, and feede vpon bread and wine not only for neceſſitie but to cheere them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; why then may not Gods children recreate themſelues by lotterie notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God hath ſanctified the ſame to end a controuerſie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:879:6"/>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we finde not in the Scriptures any diſpenſation for recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by lotterie, as wee dee for godlie mirth by ſinging, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.13. and for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and ſober chéering our ſelues by eating and drinking, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.9.10. And therefore (it being withall conſidered that the ends you ſpeake of, be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, though holy) it followeth, that God who only diſpoſeth the Lot touching the euent, and is therefore a principall actor, is not to bee ſet on worke by lotterie in any caſe but when hee diſpenſeth with vs, or giueth vs leaue ſo to doe: But diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for recreation by lotterie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewed, Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Lots may be vſed for profit in a matter of right, <hi>Num.</hi> 26.55. why not for pleaſure?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Then othes may be vſed for pleaſure, for they may for profit, in a matter of truth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.8.11. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede lots (as othes) are not to bee vſed either for profit or pleaſure, but onely to end a controuerſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>The wit is exerciſed by Table<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Cards, therefore they be no lots.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:879:7"/>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Yet Lotterie is vſed by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Dice, and by ſhufling and cutting, before the wit is exerciſed. But how doth this follow? Becauſe Cards and Tables bee not naked Lots, conſiſting only in chance (as Dice) they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no lots at all. Although (being vſed without cogging, or packing) they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt principally in chance, from whence they are to receiue denomination. In which reſpect a Lot is called in Latin <hi>Sors,</hi> that is, chance or hazard. And <hi>Lyra</hi> vpon <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. ſaith, To vſe Lots, is, by a variable euent of ſome ſenſible thing, to determine ſome doubtfull or vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine matter, as to draw cuts, or to caſt Dice. But whether you will call Cards and Tables Lots, or no, you play with chance or vſe Lotterie. Then conſider whether exerciſe of wit doth ſanctifie playing with lotterie, or playing with lotterie make ſuch exerciſing of wit a ſinne, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.13.14. For as calling God to witnes by vaine ſwearing is a ſinne, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13. ſo making God an vmpire, by playing with lotterie, muſt needs be a ſinne: yea, ſuch a ſin a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maketh the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender
<pb facs="tcp:879:7"/>(in ſome reſpects) more blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie. For there hee moe occaſions of ſwearing than of lotterie. Secondly, vaine othes moſt commonly ſlip out as vnawares, whereas lots cannot be vſed but with deliberation. Thirdly, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is to ſatiſfie other, wheras this kind of lotterie is altogether to fulfil our own luſts. Therefore take heede, that you be not guiltie of peruerting the ordinance of the Lord, of taking the name of God in vaine, and of tempting the Almightie, by a gameſome putting off things to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and making play of lotterie, except you thinke that God hath no gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in vaine actions, or hath diſpenſed with ſuch lewd games.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>In ſhooting there is a chance. by a ſudden blaſt, yet ſhooting is no lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>It is true: for that chance commeth by accident, and not of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the game, to be vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Lots are ſecret, and the whole diſpoſing of them is of God, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.33 but it is otherwiſe in Tables and Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Lots are caſt into the lap by
<pb facs="tcp:879:8"/>man, and that openly, leſt conueiance ſhould be ſuſpected: but the diſpoſing of the chance is ſecret, that it may be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce indeede, and wholly of God, who direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all things, <hi>Prou.</hi> 16.13.9.33. So in Tables, man by faire caſting Dice truly made, and in Cardes, by ſhuffling &amp; cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, doth openly diſpoſe the Dice and Cards ſo, as whereby a variable euent may follow: but it is onely and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly of God that the Dice bee ſo caſt, and the Cards ſo ſhuffled and cut, as that this or that game followeth, except there be cogging and packing. So that in faire play mans wit is not exerciſed in diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the chance, but in making the beſt of it being paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>The end of our play is recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not to make God an vmpire: but recreation (no doubt) is lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preached.</speaker>
               <p>It may be the ſouldiers had no ſuch end whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they caſt lots for Chriſt his coate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.25. but this ſhould be your end when you vſe lotterie, as the end of an oth ſhould be, to call God to witneſſe. Therefore as ſwearing, ſo lotterie, without due reſpect is ſinne.
<pb facs="tcp:879:8"/>Againe, howſoeuer recreation be your pretended end, yet remember that wee muſt not doe euill that good may come of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. And that therefore wee are to recreate our ſelues by lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations. Then ſee how Cardes and Tables be lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>If they be not abuſed by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or brawling, playing for too long time, or too much money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Though I am perſwaded that it is not lawfull to play for any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, conſidering thankes cannot be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in faith for that which is ſo gotten, <hi>Deut. 23.18. Eſa 61.8.</hi> Gameſters worke not with their hands the thing that is good, to be frée from ſtealing, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.28. and the looſer hath not anſwerable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for his money ſo loſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.15. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that equitie which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> by the light of nature hath taught long ſince, <hi>Eth. l. 5. c. 4.</hi> yet I grant that Cards and Tables ſo vſed as you ſpeak, be leſſe ſinfull, but how they bee lawfull I ſee not yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Good men and well learned vſe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:879:9"/>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>Wee muſt liue by precepts, not by examples, except they be vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly good. Therefore examine whether they bee good, &amp; well learned in ſo doing or no. For euery man may erre, <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p>It is not good to be too iuſt, or too wiſe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p>It is not good to be too wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or too fooliſh, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.19. in deſpiſing the word of God, <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.22. and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the weakneſſe of other, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.21. Let vs therefore beware that we loue not pleaſure more than godlineſſe, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:879:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
